Last month,
we saw a very popular video from the
fitness influencer Joe
Delaney,
and he talks through the economics of
fitness influencers and how some
people in the fitness industry have got
really rich.
And he quotes in his video
that some people are taking advantage of
selling
shovels in a gold rush.
I would've let this one go,
but it got personal when he put
me in the video. Really? Oh,
so that's how you're going to play it.
Firstly, I would like to clear my name.
I'm not happy with being called an
influencer,
and as Joe says in his own video,
it's a term you want to avoid in this
industry.
To me,
being a fitness influencer would be
getting in incredibly good shape so
that people associate you with stuff
and buy stuff because they want to be like
you, like selling clothes. Like,
for instance, the deal you have with Rise,
Mr.
Delaney, as an athlete, where actually,
the majority of people in the fitness
industry aspire to be a Gymshark athlete.
If I can make it
that Gymshark will let me promote their
commission
code, Mom and Dad, I've made it.
Or I would say your classic typical
influencer is
someone with really good genetics
that then does lots of brand deals.
And according to brandbookings.com, Joe,
you've done 84.
Whether or not that source is true,
I don't know.
Then the other classic fitness influencer
thing would be to get people to buy
supplements like you do here.
I like how they're under the guise of your
favor.
Rather than saying, "Hey, guys,
buy these." Like I say, Joe,
you're in incredible
shape. Now,
you and I could probably argue how much
is genetics, how much is hard
work,
or it could be the perfect blend of both.
But you and I both know
that being a fitness influencer,
promoting someone to buy
supplements,
that's prime fitness influencer.
The reason I have a gripe
is because I've never done a paid post or
endorsement in my life.
Never done a brand deal.
So when you put me in the grifter sphere,
I'm not even sure if that's a real word,
but it is now, it can trigger me a bit.
But the day you see me promoting a VPN,
Joe, I'll take the heat.
For some of you out there,
you might have realized
that I had a podcast that got
over 15 million downloads,
and I killed it because it
was losing me money.
I didn't have any sponsors.
But don't worry, it's coming back.
And I've had some insane offers over the
years.
I once got offered 80,000 pounds for a
grid post from a bank that I
didn't use. And some people said, "Oh,
but you could've just given the money to
charity." Yeah,
but then I would've had to have been a
grifter for no financial
return. So I'd say that is influencing.
Now, nevertheless, Joe's video
is actually fantastic,
and he points out a lot of
very true points about the fitness
industry.
And I agree with so much of what he's
saying,
and I actually thought this would be
a perfect opportunity to go into a little
bit more detail.
I can actually give you some details
that he wouldn't have that I have.
So let's look into revenue,
and let's start from smaller,
and we can work our way
up.
So if we go into the analytics on my
YouTube, this is the channel that I don't
particularly use that much.
1,000 pounds in a month, which wouldn't
even cover Declan's wages. And granted,
if we look at lifetime, there's
100K there.
But considering the cost of operating
and running this channel, it's
not massive.
Then if I take you to my business channel,
I don't even have
monetization turned on.
I'm just not really bothered this month to
get
126,000 views.
It's quite literally just not even worth
it.
Whether or not people get served ads
or not, if it means that a few people will
just click the video and it starts,
happy days.
And that's kind of the biggest problem
that we should probably look at to begin
with. A lot of people,
when they start on social media,
especially YouTube, they
think that they just get paid with views.
Now, if you want to be the next MrBeast
or Matt Armstrong and get a huge amount of
revenue coming in from views,
that creates a lot of stress.
Sitting there and thinking,
"That video has to go viral," for me,
stressful.
And instead, my more recent model,
which I like the most, means that here,
for
84,000 views,
I can do $13,000 in business so
far attributed.
That's just direct sales from the video,
not to mention the amount
of people that went through to lead
magnets that we'll retarget later on.
Anyway,
Joe makes a very strong point about
different advertisers spending
different amounts.
I can actually show you this.
If we look at...
Let's go lifetime.
You can see down here my most paid video.
And you can see here
that I got 20,000 pounds so far.
Is WHOOP 4 worth the hype?
Obviously,
WHOOP are paying for the advertising
privileges on that.
The AG1, four grand, four grand,
three grand.
It's all right,
but it's not enough to live off.
The majority of videos sit around the
1,000-pound range for now.
For the amount of effort, hours,
attention, planning, scripting, to
me,
that's just not a very viable business
option.
So if you want to be a YouTuber,
I would say don't do that.
I would say run your own business
and use YouTube to get clients for it,
which is
what I now do.
So any of the monetization
that I get from the big channel, I
actually give half to Declan,
just because then it'll motivate him to
maybe make
the edit a little bit sweeter. And also,
I should be able to incentivize him that
he wants me to win.
If he wants me to win because it allows
him to win, then I'll
probably win. Anyway,
then we get into what can only be
described as the
personal trainer villain arc
or the fitness influencer villain arc,
selling
your own stuff. Granted,
I had my first taste of this the last few
years with
NoTonic, which we'll get into in a second,
and then there are, of course, the
books. However, for the first seven,
eight years of my career, I could say that
every single penny
that I'd ever earned had come through
education.
If it wasn't a book or an event
or coaching, it wasn't anything else.
Now, Joe, in his video,
talks about a company called Genflow,
of which I use with
NoTonic and with my mentorship.
One thing I would say here
is Joe says they
build businesses for influencers,
and I would disagree.
Yes,
Genflow are a business partner in my
business mentorship, but what they're
doing is actually helping me in an area
where I don't want to have many staff.
For instance,
I don't want to have to go to a web
developer every time I want to
put something new on the platform.
I don't want to have to deal with having
an agency to run my paid ads.
I don't want to have to deal with all
kinds of different areas
and administrative
areas.
I just don't want to have to deal with so
many different places and have
them all reporting to me. Not to mention,
I don't want to have an ads guy who's
working on loads of projects at other
times.
And Genflow have been fantastic for me for
this.
So for instance, some of the courses
that I have with Genflow right now, the
content mastery course,
I have an email marketing course,
I have a chatbot course.
I even have one that helps you design your
bio.
Then inside the actual mentorship,
there are all kinds of different lessons
about
all kinds of different things,
and even Genflow help me managing my very
large
Discord community.
And it's nice to have someone on board
that also cares.
For instance,
there's a lad called Connor
that works for Genflow.
He'll respond to me at 11:00 PM.
And because he earns money based off his
performances for our ads,
it's great to know
that there's someone that's literally
on it and invested into it. So Genflow
are a business partner,
and they take quite
a modest cut compared to what some other
business partners take.
Let's look at my coaching app,
Affordable Online Training.
It used to be called James Smith Academy,
but we rebranded because the only
question that people used to ask
is what is it,
because I called it an academy.
So here, this platform,
we've got a state-of-the-art app.
We've had over 100,000 members, of
which at the moment we've probably got
about
7,000 active. And I'll be honest with you,
this business does about a million
pounds a year. It's a great amount,
but at the same time, it's not greedy.
There's literally two of us running it.
We've got an amazing group of coaches.
We pay them based on the amount of work
that they're doing, which means that they
can have their own clients,
they can have their families,
they can jump in when
they want, jump out when they want,
and we get some pretty amazing results
from
that. Not to mention,
when it comes to our pricing,
we have plans that start from
10 pound a month So before any of you
think that we're some kind of capitalistic
pigs that are trying to capitalize on
selling workouts, £10 a month, you can get
all your workouts taken care of. Now,
the one thing that I would say, another
business lesson here,
you're going to need business partners.
You are.
And even the idea of maybe giving 20% of
your business away can seem really
daunting, but then yet, in the UK,
you're happy to pay VAT on everything,
which is
20% just gone.
Sometimes having partners
that care about your business, as Joe says
in his videos, means
that you can concentrate on things
that are really important.
For instance, making this video right now.
Because making this video means I can put
links in the description, we can get the
edit done, we can do everything.
And any administrative task
that can be handled by
Genflow is probably being handled by
Genflow.
So I would like to argue on behalf of all
the people using Genflow, that they are
operating their own businesses.
The partnership they have just means
that we get to
offload the things
that we shouldn't have to worry about.
Now,
we're about to step foot into my
multimillion-dollar villain arc.
That Joe is maybe having a little pop at,
and he's fair to.
He 100% can say what he said.
But let's make something clear.
I used to personal train in person.
Done thousands of hours on the floor.
I started in a budget gym called
Absolutely Fitness,
which doesn't even make sense.
It was £19 a month, and it
was in a business park in Bracknell in the
UK.
I scaled a PT business,
which again took years to understand.
Charge more money, build demand,
keep clients happy,
get them the results you want.
From that,
I then scaled into an online digital
business, again, to be able to
provide programs for £10 a month.
And the current trajectory of my career,
it
wasn't sustainable.
I either had a lot of people paying a lot
of money, giving them
a shit service,
or build the affordable online coaching,
formerly JSA app.
Then,
the next way to pivot the business
was writing books.
You make about a pound a book.
Which doesn't seem like a lot, granted.
You do get a good cash advance upfront.
£100,000 for "Not a Diet Book," maybe 150
for "Not a Life Coach"
or maybe 200 for "How to be Confident."
And the advance you get means
that you have
to sell a certain amount before you can
get royalties.
So I think we had to sell 55,000 hardbacks
for "Not a Diet Book" before the £1
royalty started kicking in.
Probably sold about a million books.
And again, that sounds amazing.
A million pounds.
But then my manager,
also 20% of everything.
After tax,
you've got a fair whack to put down for a
deposit on a house, sure.
But it's a lot of work
that goes into them.
Then we have the events.
Now,
you'll often see me putting up photos of
the Hammersmith Apollo.
And the reason that the Hammersmith Apollo
was such an important big thing for me
was it was 3,500 people. It
was the biggest event I'd done.
I'd gone through a run of events
beforehand.
And it also just so happens to be the very
first event in which my parents ever
came to. Now, that night,
over £100,000 for a night's work.
Again, you say £100,000.
You've got production,
stage, staff, ticketing, VAT, tax, all
of these kind of things
that people don't really think about.
But you still sold £100,000 worth of
tickets in a single night to an event
where
you're talking about a book
that you got a fat advance for,
that they've had to buy
as well. And here's the crazy thing.
On the night that we sold the Hammersmith
Apollo, we actually had sold more tickets
to events than we had pre-orders for the
book.
What you make of
that just goes to show
that maybe I'm better at selling some
things than others.
So let's look at why I've made the villain
arc migration
into business to business,
which means I'm now helping small
businesses at the same
time. I'll be honest with you,
ads never worked for me.
My coaching app, every year,
we spend more in Stripe fees than we do in
ads.
Up until when I started working with
Genflow, I also never had staff.
I recorded everything myself.
I edited everything myself.
I had no marketing team,
no marketing department.
All I've ever had was a manager.
Every component of running a seven-figure
business, I've had a business partner,
but I do all the marketing
and sales elements of it myself.
Never had assistance with content.
Had to teach myself how to use Premiere
Pro, cameras, lighting, audio, everything.
So what I'm selling to people
is how to operate a business solo,
how to come up
with ideas on your own,
how to grow your PT business on your own.
Because I didn't have anyone else helping
me back in the day.
I did the odd course here and there.
I studied under Paul Moore for a bit to
learn him my marketing, but that was it.
I also charge about 3,000 USD for lifetime
access to my business mentorship.
When I do one-to-one calls,
I get 1,000 USD an hour.
And again, I think that's a rip-off,
but people pay it because
if I give them five
actionable points in their business
and they go away and do it,
they can make way
more than that,
not to mention they're writing off the
cost.
Because when people use your fitness app,
they can't write off that cost.
When people use me in a business capacity,
their business pays for it.
It just reduces their profitability.
I made the majority of all the money I've
ever made running my own things, saying
no to brand deals and endorsements,
saying no to paid ads.
That's what people are paying me for.
No bags of protein sold,
no Gymshark endorsements.
Not selling how to get womp
and get people to pay you to wear clothes.
I'm not selling protein for big muscles,
swipe up.
I'm selling how to grow a solo business
because I've done it, not because I see an
opportunity to sell shovels in a gold
rush.
And now, Joe,
I also disagree with you here.
This is probably the thing
that I disagree with you the absolute
most.
You say that you don't want to step into
B2B because you don't want to make
PowerPoint presentations. And whether
or not that's just banter or potentially
naivety, let me say this. You
are an excellent YouTuber,
an excellent storyteller,
an excellent presenter. Your scripting
is fantastic. You've got a great rig.
I would actually argue the fact
that you're not offering any of your
audience
anything in this realm
is potentially a disservice to them.
Because think about it this way.
You've learnt a lot about training
and fitness,
and you've developed lots of concepts as a
coach, and you now sell that to people
so they can be inspired by it
and learn from everything
that you've done. Correct?
So maybe it's a bench technique,
maybe it's the way you do programming.
You've learnt all of this yourself.
You now sell it in your app.
But you've also got one of the best
YouTube accounts in the entire industry.
So here's a question for you, Joe.
If I got an aspiring YouTuber
and I put him with
you for the day and all you spoke about
was YouTube, would that YouTuber become
better at YouTube? Almost definitely yes.
Even if they didn't learn anything
and they just got inspired by being within
your
energy for the day.
Because I've done that.
I've been to events before where I've not
learnt anything new, but I've met a
mentor in the fitness industry.
I've realized they're just a normal
person, and
it's inspired me to do more.
And even watching your content,
you're making me
question my scenes, my shots, whether
or not I should be putting music in to
create
the emotional tone.
Every minute of me watching your content
is making me actually
want to level up. Now,
a day with you for a YouTuber would
probably cost a fortune
because you've showed us what you get paid
for other things, right?
But if you were to create a basic YouTube
content creation course and sold it for
299 USD,
you could see the people following you
could make a
tremendous return on investment from
that course.
You could make money passively.
All you'd need to say in videos is, "Oh,
if you enjoyed this video, I can teach you
how to make them.
Check out the link in the description."
Because if they don't
learn from you,
they're going to learn from someone else
who's probably going to
charge them a lot more
and rip them off a lot more.
You seem like a humble guy.
You don't seem like you want Lambos
and Ferraris and whatever.
So why not be that person? Not to mention,
like I said before, they could write
that course off against their business,
not them paying it for it,
because with the
protein and rise and the clothing,
they're paying.
But for this, their business can-...
could pay.
If you can inspire people to get into
fitness and training,
why can't you inspire
people to start a YouTube channel
and start a business?
Actually,
do you really think you've made it this
far without inspiring anyone to
do what you're doing?
That's surely a morally better deal than
flogging
supplements. We know modern days
that almost no supplements that
are sold in powder form
and bags online are actually being tested,
and if they are,
they're often pretty far out from what
they're supposed to be.
You say in your video
that personal training
and coaching isn't really a viable way
to make a lot of money, and again,
I kind of disagree here.
I think we need to look at it into four
tiers for anyone watching.
Tier one,
people must get good at in-person
coaching.
Without in-person coaching,
you've not really got anything to sell.
Then people should look to migrate to do
mostly in-person and a bit online.
Then you can be a bit more selective with
your hours.
Just go to the gym from 6:00 a.m.
till 1:00 p.m.
and refuse to work afternoons.
Work with clients from a laptop.
Then your attitude
and happiness to be in the
gym will only improve.
If you make your relationship to work feel
more like play,
you're just going to enjoy it more.
Being in the gym for 12 hours a day
is just not sustainable.
Tier three for some, not everyone,
they can go fully online,
where it gets to the
point that it doesn't make sense for them
to go sell hours for money.
Because the truth is,
if you're very good at a coach
and you do what you do, you
can service clients a lot quicker than you
can in person.
In person, it's always an hour. Online,
some weeks you can get a client done in 20
minutes, sometimes an hour,
whatever it is.
Then tier four, beyond that,
would be scaling an online business where
you bring in
coaches, get them to do the work.
Which can seem like I'm some evil
capitalist, but
like I said, my coaches have got lives.
They don't want to be on social media.
They don't want to become Instagram
famous.
They just want to help people,
write people's programs and chat to them,
and be
able to jump in and out when they want.
So when they go on holiday,
they can go on holiday,
and they haven't got to worry
about food being served on the table.
I'm going to win over business
that they can use.
And then tier five,
or let's call it tier 4.5,
would be scaling a business.
So let's say you bring in other people to
work for you to the point you can then
pivot in other directions,
whether it's books, events, whatever.
And anyone out there that's made it to
tier four, 4.5 should be
helping other people, including yourself,
Joe.
I train Brazilian jujitsu,
and I started with the sole purpose of
just getting good
at jujitsu. It's all I care about.
Becoming very, very good and competent.
However, ever since hitting brown belt,
20% to 30% of my time at training is now
helping lower belts because it's my
service too. It actually benefits me.
If people in my gym get better at jujitsu,
I have better training partners, the
same way that if you then take it upon you
to make better YouTubers, YouTube
becomes better.
And a more competitive landscape is good.
If anything, in capitalism,
that's one of the main principles of
things being
affordable is there
is an equal amount of competition.
Competition,
all of good competence levels brings
pricing down.
It's when there's only one outlier
that does better than everyone else
that you
can't compete and prices become
extortionate.
So I now spend my time in the training
room in jujitsu telling people what they
did
right,
what they did wrong because I'm a natural
coach, as I'm sure you are too.
Now, I could be a villain.
I could be a sellout.
I could be someone just selling those
shovels in a gold rush.
But here's actually some clips from some
of my clients of what they said about
working with me.
So would I recommend James' course?
Absolutely, without a shadow of a doubt.
James, thank you so much.
You really changed my life.
Having a mentor like James in your corner
is like
having a fast-track pass at Disneyland.
The support inside the mentorship from
James and all the other
members is like nothing I've ever seen.
I stuck at 3K followers,
and within five months, I was able to hit
20K. James helped me with my content,
and by the end of March, I had over
100,000 followers.
And then there's my other businesses.
Nutonic that I spoke about before.
We're currently at a $20 million valuation
when we last raised about six months
ago. Again, that's not money in the bank.
So although technically that's worth what
you would have called five figures,
that's promising, but again,
doesn't mean anything.
Then we've got my investment into Manual,
which is my TRT deal, but it's not a
deal.
I've not earned one penny from Manual so
far.
My position is to grow the business,
but I could've all too easily just said to
Manual, "Yeah, give me 50 grand.
I'll endorse it." But I didn't.
I said, "Give me nothing.
Let me help you grow the business,
and in five years'
time, let's see where we're at." And
if they exit, maybe a payday, maybe not.
We'll see.
But I'm going to close on something
that I've not really shared before.
I used to wonder the same as you.
How do all these fitness influencers have
so much
money? And I'll never forget the day
that I did 14 PT sessions in a day.
I left. I was dead. You cannot do
that many in a day and survive.
And I saw Joe Wicks gloating about the
fact he made a million pound a month,
and I
was jealous. I was outraged. I
was pissed off.
But I didn't just get annoyed by it.
I did something about it, and you can too.
You can do something about it.
Everyone's going to be bitter at people
doing better than them, but there's going
to be a small group of people
that want to change that,
that want to improve, that
want to take it to the next level.
And I'm not super rich.
I've still got a GT3 instead of a GT3 RS.
I've still got an RS Q8 instead of an
Urus. Still man of the people.
But I'm actually in the best zone
possible.
At 36,
I have everything I want in my life.
Everything.
Everything from here up is just bullshit.
That first Lambo, bullshit.
And although it can seem from the outside
like a villain arc, think of it this way.
First part of my career,
I see people in the gym putting in the
effort, putting in
the yards, getting the sweat on,
but they could do it better.
So I came in, bit like you, Joe,
helped them with what they're doing so
they could
put the same time, energy,
and effort in and get a better result.
I now do the exact same thing in business.
I come in. I look at the program.
I'm like, "Whoa,
let's change this amount of volume.
Let's put your focus here.
Let's change this in your diet."
And then people can get better results
from the
effort they're currently putting in.
I often say to people,
if I can take your conversion on a landing
page from 1% to
2%,
that's double the amount of money for the
same energy, time, and effort.
I do what I'm doing, Joe,
because I'm a coach, as are you.
I just now coach different things.
If you come to training at jujitsu,
I will coach you jujitsu.
If I see you in the gym,
I'll coach you how to do a bench press.
And if I hear you talking about a business
idea, I'll coach you through the
concept, the social media ideation,
how we'll get email addresses, the launch,
and
what that offer's going to look like on
the landing page.
Because once you get good at one thing in
life, your skills are very transferable.
If you don't think what I'm learning in
jujitsu on my road to a black belt
is going
to help me in business, you're naïve.
If you don't think what you learn in
building a PT business empire helps other
businesses, you're an idiot.
So it's an important consideration for
people to
understand.
That first chunk of building a business,
starting a YouTube channel,
going from zero to one
is the hardest thing,
and we should all be trying to help
people the best we can.
Because once you get good at
that one thing, you can flip
it into so many other things. There
are links to what I do in the description.
You can click on them.
Don't have to click on them.
There's some free stuff in there as well.
And this video is brought to you by...
Just messing.
I'll do the classic YouTuber thing
and just point at the video that
you should watch after this
if you're not interested.
Thanks for watching.